let's work on some problems calculate
the force of gravity that exists between
a 60 kgam person and an 80 kgam person
who are 50 cm apart from each other so
let's draw a
picture so let's say that this is the 60
kilogram
person and here is the 80 kilog person
how can we calculate the gravitational
force between the two now gravity is a
force of attraction gravity brings
matters
together so gravity is going to pull the
60 kilogram person towards the 80
kilogram person and the 60 kilogram
person exerts a force on the 80 kgam
person and so these two forces they're
equal in magnitude but opposite in
direction and this represents the force
of gravity now the way to calculate it
is to use this equation it's equal to G
time the mass of the first person times
the mass of the second person divided by
the distance between
them and that distance has to be squared
now the distance between them is 50
cm and we need to convert that to meters
1 meter is 100 cm so 50
cm is equivalent to .5 M you got to
divide
100 G is a universal gravitation
constant it's
6.67 * 10- 11 and the
units are Newtons Time Square met /
Square
kilog so let's go ahead and calculate
the gravitational force so it's going to
be
6.67 * 10 -
11 time the first mass which is 60 kg
time the second mass of 80 / the square
of the distance which is5 M
squ so the answer is very small it's
1.28 * 10 to the- 6
Newtons so that's the force of gravity
between these two individuals
number two calculate the force of
gravity of a 25 kg block resting on the
earth and we're given the radius of the
Earth so let's say this is the
Earth and we have a block resting on it
what's the force of gravity that is
exerted on that block which points
towards the center of the
earth how can we calculate
so to calculate the gravitational force
we can use this equation G M1 * M2 R
2 so G is
6.67 *
101 and the mass of the first block is
25 the mass of the earth is
5.97 * 10 24
kg and the distance between the center
of the block and the center of the earth
is is approximately the radius of the
Earth the block is going to be
relatively small so we could say it's
about the radius of the Earth which is
6.38 * 10
6 and don't forget to
square so let's type this in
so the gravitational force is
so it's 25 *
9.8 and you get about 245
Newtons so these answers are about the
same so this is the most easiest way to
find the weight force of an object on
any Planet if you know the gravitational
acceleration of that
planet now let's work on this problem
what is the force of gravity that is ex
deserted on the Earth by the Sun so
we're given the mass of the Sun and the
Earth and the distance between them so
let's start with a picture so let's say
that's the Sun and this is the
Earth so the Sun is going to exert a
gravitational force on the Earth the Sun
is going to pull the Earth toward itself
and the Earth pulls the sun toward
itself those two forces are equal in
magnitude but opposite in direction so
we need to calculate those two forces
now we're given the distance between the
center of the Earth and the Sun and
that's 1. 1496 * 10^ 11
M we have the masses as well so all we
need to do is plug everything in into
this
equation so G is
6.67 *
10-1 and the mass of the Sun is
1.99 * 10 to the 30 kg and the mass of
the earth is
5.97 * 10 24
kilog and let's divide it by R 2 so
that's the square of the distance
between them
so you should get a gravitational
force of
3.54 * 10 22
Newtons so that's the force that the sun
exerts on the earth and it's also the
force that the Earth
exerts on the sun they're the
same now let's move on to number four
Planet X and Planet y have a mass of 3 *
10 24 kg and 4.5 * 10 25 kgam so let's
draw a
picture so let's say this is Planet
X and this is planet
y now we're given the gravitational
force
between these two
planets our goal is to find the
distance between the two planets and R
is going to represent the distance
between the center of Planet X to the
center of Planet
y so let's start with this
equation and let's rearrange it to
isolate the R value so I'm going to
multiply both sides by R 2
so on the right side these will cancel
and so I have f * r^ 2 is equal to G M1
* M2 so next I'm going to divide both
sides by F and so R 2 is G M1 M2 / f now
the last thing I need to do is take the
square root of both sides so R is going
to be the square root of G M1 M2 over f
so let's go ahead and get the
answer so that's going to be
6.67 *
101 multiplied by the mass of Planet
X which is 3 * 10 24 * the mass of
planet Y which is 4.5 * 10
25 and then we need to divide it by the
gravitational force that's acting on
these two
planets and that's 3.6 * 10 20 newtons
so the answer is about 5.0 * 10
9 so it's about 5 billion
meters so that's the distance between
the two planets between the centers
number five calculate the net force
exerted on the moon when it's between
the Earth and the Sun and we're given
the distance between the Moon and the
Earth and the distance between the Sun
and the Moon so let's draw a picture so
we're going to say this is the
Sun and this is the moon and here's the
Earth
now the Sun is going to exert a
gravitational force on the moon and it's
going to pull it towards the sun let's
call it FS the force that the sun exerts
on the moon and the earth also pulls the
moon toward itself let's call it
Fe our goal is to calculate the net
force the net force is going to be the
difference between these two
forces based on the way it's drawn Fe is
pointed in a positive X Direction so
that's going to be positive and Fs is in
a Negative X Direction so I'm going to
put a negative sign in front of it so
because these two forces are
anti-parallel the net force is the
difference between those two
forces so let's go ahead and calculate
Fe
first so it's going to be G times the
mass of the Earth multiplied by the mass
of the Moon because this force is
between the Earth and the Moon
divided by the square of the distance
between them so that's
6.67 *
101 the mass of the earth is
5.97 * 10^
24 and the mass of the Moon is
7.35 * 10 22
kg and the distance between the Moon and
the
Earth that's
3.84 * 10 8 m and let's Square it as
well so let's go ahead and type this
in so you should get
1.9 85 * 10 20 nton so that's the force
that that the Earth exerts on the moon
towards the
right now let's calculate
FS so it's going to be G times the mass
of the Moon times the mass of the Sun /
the square of the
distance so G is not going to change
it's the same value 6.67 * 10- 11 the
mass of the moon is still 7.35 * 10
22 and the mass of the Sun is 1.99 * 10^
kilg now the distance between the Sun
and the Moon is given to us that's 1.
1492 * 10 11^ SAR
so you should get a
force of
4.38 3 * 10 20
newtons so now that we have these two
forces we can now calculate the net
force
so the net force is going to be Fe which
is 1.9 85 * 10 20 minus FS which is
4383 * 10 to the
20 and so this is going to be negative
2398 * 10^ 20
newtons now the reason why we have a
negative sign is because the net force
is directed towards the left towards the
negative X Direction and so what that
means is that this Force FS is greater
than
Fe so the gravitational force exerted by
the sun on the moon is greater than the
gravitational force exerted by the Earth
on a moon during a solar eclipse for
example when the moon blocks the
sun relative to the
Earth so the Moon is being pulled more
towards the Sun than the
Earth and the reason why that happens is
because the mass of the Sun is so much
more larger than the mass of the Earth
even though the distance between the
Earth and the moon is a lot less than
the between the Sun and the Moon but the
mass of the Sun is just a lot
larger but as we can see these two
values are very
close so the gravitational force exerted
by the sun on the moon is a little bit
more than twice the gravitational force
exerted by the Earth on the
moon but nevertheless in this situation
this force is greater so the moon fills
a net force that pulls it towards the
Sun
number six what is the net force exerted
on the Moon by the Earth and the sun
when the two gravitational forces acting
on the moon are at right angles to each
other so how can we find the answer to
this
question well let's draw a picture just
like we did before so let's say this is
the
Sun and we're going to have to put the
moon at this position let me draw a
little bit bigger and let's place the
Earth
here now we want the two forces acting
on the moon to be at right angles with
each
other you could put the Earth here if
you want to it won't change your
answer now the Sun is going to pull the
moon toward
itself and the Earth is going to pull
the moon towards the Earth and so these
two forces are at right angles and so
there's going to be a net force that is
going to be directed in that direction
now we know the force of the sun exerted
on the moon is going to be greater than
the force of the earth exerted on
it and based on the last
example the values shouldn't be that
different
so let's rewrite the values that we had
in problem
five Fe was
1.9 85 * 10^ 20
newtons and
Fs that was
4.38 3 * 10 20
newtons so let's calculate the net
force so I'm going to redraw this
picture
so here's the net force it's going to be
the hypotenuse of the right triangle FS
is in the X Direction f is in the y
direction so regardless of how you draw
it you can also draw it this way if you
want you can say here's a net
force here's
fs and this is Fe this is still the
hypotenuse so the net force is going to
be the square root of the square of FS
plus the square of Fe
so this is going to be
4.3 83 * 10 20
2ar
plus 1.
1985 * 10 20
2ar all right so let's go ahead and get
the answer
so the net
force is equal to
4.81 2 * 10^ 20
newtons so that's the net force acting
on the earth I mean on the moon when
it's at this
position for